Okay, here's 11 calcium channel blockers.
Another top 10 through pajamas.
But the good news about this one, there isn't a whole lot you need to know.
You just have to know some basics about these heart drugs.
Somewhere in the margin of this lecture, I want you to write the following.
Calcium channel blockers are like valium for your heart.
Why would I say that?
I think that makes it easy for you to remember what they do.
Because what does valium do for your body and for you in general?
What's a good one?
It calms you down.
So what do you think calcium channel blockers do to the heart?
They calm it down.
So if you get a question about a calcium channel blocker, think, oh, that's going to calm my
heart down.
That would be just like giving my heart some valium.
Now did I say it was valium?
No, it's not valium.
It's nothing to do with valium.
But it's like valium for your heart.
So if your heart is tachycardic, could it stand a little relaxing?
So what class of drug could you give?
Calcium channel blocker.
If you're in shock, does your heart need to relax when you're in shock?
No, you need to get cooking here.
So would you give a calcium channel blocker?
No.
If your heart was in heart block, would you give a calcium channel blocker?
If your heart was having tachyrhythmias, would you give a calcium channel blocker?
So if you had a heart attack and you wanted to rest your heart, what would you give?
Calcium channel blocker.
So calcium channel blocker is given when you want to rest your heart.
When your heart needs stimulated, please don't give a calcium channel blocker.
That's not a good idea.
So this is like valium for your heart.
How do we say that really fancy?
The way we say that fancy is the follows.
You see here where it says letter A, calcium channel blockers are negative, inotropic,
chronotropic, andromotropic.
When you see the fancy words negative, inotropic, negative, chronotropic, negative, dromotropic,
don't freak out.
All that's saying is what?
It's like valium for your heart.
So negative inotropes, negative chronotropes, negative dromotropes relax your heart.
They calm it down.
Now the chart below shows you the difference between the positive inotrope, chronotrope,
dromatropes, and the negative inotrope, chronotrope, dromatropes.
What do positive chrono-inodromos do?
Look down through them.
What do they do?
They strengthen, speed up, stimulate.
So they are called what?
Cardiac, depressants, or stimulants?
And negatives are cardiac depressants.
So a positive inochronodromotrope is a cardiac stimulant.
And a negative inochronodromo is a cardiac depressant.
Do you see the difference?
In that chart, which column should you highlight in this lecture because it applies to the
calcium channel blockers?
The last column.
So circle and highlight the last column because that's where calcium channel blockers fit
into the picture.
They're negative inochronodromatropes.
They weaken, slow down, and depress the heart.
Letter B. When would we want to do that?
What do they treat?
Well, they treat A, AA, and AAA.
The letter A is your friend here.
A, AA, and AAA.
Well what does A stand for?
Number one, they are antihypertensives.
They are antihypertensives.
How does that work?
They relax your heart and blood vessels.
If you relax your heart and relax your blood vessels, what does your blood pressure do?
It goes down.
Does that make sense?
If your blood pressure was high, would you take a value for your heart or a stimulant
for your heart?
If your blood pressure's high, would you want a balance for your heart or a stimulant
A balance.
And that would mean you'd use a calcium channel blocker.
Do you see what I'm talking about?
The second AA stands for antianginols.
They are antiangina drugs.
Well how does that work?
It's going to relax your heart so it uses less oxygen so there goes the angina way.
It works by decreasing oxygen demand.
It treats angina by decreasing oxygen demand because it relaxes the heart.
What's the worst thing in the world for a person with angina?
What's the worst thing that can happen to a person with angina?
With our heart.
What's the worst thing that can happen to their heart?
Is it a person with angina?
Speed up.
And then as problems, so you want to do what to the heart?
Slow it down.
AAA.
Anti atrial arrhythmia.
So what does it treat?
Will it treat ventricular tachycardia?
No.
Why?
Because that's ventricular and this only treats atrial.
Will it treat atrial flutter?
Yes.
Atrial fibrillation?
Premature ventricular contractions?
No.
Premature atrial contractions?
Yes.
Paroxysmal atrial tachycardia?
Atrial bi-gemini?
Yes.
Ventricular bi-gemini?
No.
Oh, there you go.
I love medical transcriptionists that don't know what they're writing.
We always have fun reading those charts on night shift.
Remember one time I had to work at night, I was excited, that's what struck me up.
We were reading this guy's history in physical and the doctor dictated it and the transcriptionist
wrote out the history in physical, you know, and they make mistakes.
He said that this guy had...
This guy has ventricular bi-gemini.
It's a lot of fun.
Okay.
So all you have to know to know what a rhythm is this treat is to know if it starts with
what letter?
A.
If it's an A, it's yes.
And if it's a B, it's no.
But there's a trick.
What about this one?
Supra ventricular tachycardia, SVT.
Would calcium channel blockers treat SVT?
Yes or no?
I'm going to say yes.
You're correct.
Yes.
Why?
What does supra mean?
And what's above the ventricles?
A.
B.
So it's supraventricular is the only ventricular which is actually saying atrial.
Does everybody get that?
Otherwise you're good to go.
Because it treats A, A, A, and A, A, A.
Well what are the side effects?
H and H.
The letter H is your friend here.
Headache and hypo tension.
Why hypo tension?
Because it relaxes the heart and the blood vessels.
Why the headache?
Because you get vasodilation in the brain and that gives you like a migraine.
By the way, headache is a great thing to check on a select all that apply.
What do you have with low sodium?
Any.
What do you have with a high sodium?
Heading.
What do you have with a high glucose?
What do you have with a low glucose?
Heading.
What do you have with high blood pressure?
What do you have with a low blood pressure?
Heading.
You know, I mean, headache is pretty, I'm going with headache.
Ugh, I know.
N said the person.
And the other one.
That's the one.
And the other one, I said the other one, I said the other one, I said the other one,
the other one, the other one, the other one, the other one, the other one, the other one,
Anything ending in Dipene.
Amlode Dipene, Nifed Dipene, the Dippings.
I always say you're dipping in the calcium channel.
Not peeing. Why not peeing?
Why do I not want you to memorize everything ending in P?
Because there are loads of drugs that end in P that are not things.
It has to be a Dipene. Dipene. Dipene is your calcium channel blocker ending.
And then there are two others you have to know by name.
Barapamil and cardizem. Barapamil and cardizem.
So the Dipenes, Barapamil and cardizem. Dipenes, Barapamil, cardizem.
Those are your calcium channel blockers.
Which of those is continuous IV drip? Can be given. Can be given. Cardizem.
So when you give a calcium channel blocker, now think about this.
When you give a calcium channel blocker, what vital sign do you need to measure before you give it?
Blood pressure. Why? What's the side effect? Hypotension. Hypotension.
So you measure the blood pressure. What are your parameters? What are your guidelines?
You get a blood pressure. So what? What are your guidelines? How are you going to use it?
For no women, I'm thinking the heart.
You're thinking false. You're thinking false right now. Not that.
Okay. Which one?
Yes. Hold the calcium channel blocker if the systolic, that's the top number, is under 100.
Take the blood pressure. Don't take it. Measure the blood pressure.
And if the systolic is under 100, then you hold the calcium channel blocker.
So what do you have to monitor continuously or fairly quickly, intermittently while they're on a cardizem drip?
The blood pressure. And there again, if it was 98 over 52, what would you do?
What would you do with the drip?
Slow it down. Measure it again. So you titrate. Do you know what I mean by titrate?
Change the IV rate to keep the blood pressure what? Systolic over 100.
LPNs, they would say if somebody's on a cardizem drip, you notice all the following.
Which one would you report to the RN? It's the systolic falling below 100.
Same information just to ask from a different perspective.
Okay. Cardiac arrhythmias. The ones that we're going to do for the rest of the night are short.
So that you're, you know, I, if the day goes on in your brain, it's more spaghetti-like.
And I just want to keep it faster so you don't get no belongings in the middle of the night.
Cardiac arrhythmias. Knowing how to interpret rhythm strips.
Now turn to page 13, the next page down. Next page.
You see at the bottom of the page there are four rhythm strip tracings.
These are the four you must know by sight. You have to know these by sight.
The first one is normal sinus rhythm. How do you know it is normal sinus rhythm?
There's a P wave, a QRS, and a T wave for every single complex.
There's a P wave before every QRS, and every QRS is followed by a T wave.
But what else tells you it is normal sinus rhythm?
Do you see the peaks of the P waves? How equally distant they are from one another?
That tells you you're not dealing with something called a sinus arrhythmia.
So that is normal sinus rhythm because there's a P for every QRS,
and the QRS complexes are evenly spaced.
When you see that, that's normal sinus rhythm.
It doesn't really matter if they go up or down.
You can have a P wave going up, QRS going down. That's okay. That's still normal sinus.
The second one is the fib, ventricular fibrillation.
It is a chaotic squiggly line.
The third one, it looks like a 1970s wallpaper border.
That's V-tach, ventricular tachycardia.
It's got those sharp peaks and jacks.
Is there a pattern? Yeah.
Is there a pattern with ventricular fibrillation?
No. There's no pattern with V-fib. There is a pattern with V-tach.
The last one is called what?
A-cystole. Please don't miss that one.
I got a lot of things. Don't miss it.
I mean, you're going to go down and down. Big time.
Crash and burn time.
Okay, let's go back to page 12.
Now, I just want to hit those right off the gate.
Now, could they show you Wolf-Parkinson-White syndrome?
Yeah.
But why do I not teach you that?
You don't need to know it.
But Mark, you said, if they show it to me, don't I need to know it?
What's the answer?
No.
What do you need to know?
You need to know the answers to the questions that everybody else knows.
And everybody else knows what A-cystole looks like.
And everybody else knows what V-fib looks like.
And everybody else knows what V-tach looks like.
And everybody else knows what normal science looks like.
Nobody else knows what Wolf-Parkinson-White syndrome looks like.
So if you miss that, it doesn't hurt you.
You understand?
These questions are all given degrees of difficulty.
So do you have to get every question right?
No. What questions do you have to get right?
The ones that everybody knows.
The easy questions.
You can miss every single hard question on the boards and pass with flying colors.
You understand what I'm saying?
So why do I teach you what I teach you?
I want to teach you the stuff that everybody knows.
So that you real quickly get correct the answers to the questions that everybody else knows.
So that real quickly you get to what kind of questions?
Hard ones that no one knows.
Now you're going to feel how?
Horrible because you don't know any of this stuff.
But that's good.
Do you know what I'm saying?
I want my goal is to, as fast as I can, get you to the hard questions.
The questions that nobody else knows including you.
So that you feel really stupid.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
I want you to, halfway through this test I want you to be going, what?
What is that drug?
What disease is that?
What are you talking about?
Who's that?
What's this?
Because you understand, you don't have to know everything.
You just have to know what everybody else knows.
What, you know, a little less than average.
And so we're not going to, that's what kills me about a lot of these review books.
A lot of these review books have all these rhythm strips in it, which is ridiculous.
And these people have to memorize these rhythm strips like 50 of them.
And only four of them really are going to hurt you if you don't know.
So why do these other books put those rhythm strips in their review?
Why do they put them in there?
Because they what?
Heard that they're on there.
They heard that they're on there.
And so they what?
They heard that something's on there.
So what do they do immediately in their book?
They throw it in.
And their books get what?
They're going to think they're good.
My books are what?
Then let's focus on the stuff you need to know.
And not the crazy stuff.
I always say there's three levels of nursing knowledge.
Stuff you need to know, stuff that's nice to know, and stuff that's nuts to know.
And most of nursing books are made up of nuts to know.
Have you ever asked a teacher, just tell me what I need to know.
And they say, well, read the book in the notes.
Well, that's helpful.
Well, part of what you're paying me for is to take all of that that's in those books
and narrow it down to this.
So if you know this, you know what everybody else knows.
And soon you'll get to stuff that no one knows.
You won't know everything, but hey, that's cool.
So don't think you have to know everything.
Because if you try to learn everything, you'll master nothing.
Did you hear what I said?
If you try to learn everything, you'll master nothing.
And that's what students do.
They just try to learn more and more and more and more and more.
No, more isn't the solution.
Okay?
Focusing on what you really need to know and then how to apply it.
That's what we're talking about.
Okay?
Back on page 12a, terminology.
Whenever the question says QRS depolarization, it's talking about ventricular.
If it says blankly, blank, blank, blank, blank, QRS depolarization is blank, blank, blank, blank, blank.
You can always narrow it down to one of two.
Both of those would say what word?
Ventricular.
You can rule out anything that says what?
Atrial.
If you see QRS, you can rule out anything that says ventricular.
I atrial and go with what's ventricular.
However, number two, if it says P wave, that will refer to something atrial and you can rule out anything ventricular.
Unless they say a lack of a P wave.
Well, I mean, that's not really talking about a P wave.
All right, let's use that to answer letter B, the six rhythms most tested on end clamps.
Number one, they will use this phrase, a lack of QRSs.
There are no QRSs.
Zero, none.
What do you think that's called?
A systole.
That's a flat line.
That's a systole.
Number two has to be a form of what?
Atrial.
Why does it have to be atrial?
It's P wave.
It's that P wave.
And when you see sawtooth, you always pick flutter.
Flutter is always described as sawtooth.
I always think of the movie Jaws.
I saw the teeth and my heart did flutter.
Sawtooth, flutter.
Numbers three and four, do you notice the day of the same adjective, the word chaotic?
Chaotic is always the word used to describe fibrillation.
Fibrillation.
So what is number three?
Ventricular.
How do you know it's atrial?
P1.
And what's number four?
Ventricular fibrillation.
How did you know it was ventricular?
P2.
How did you know it was fibrillation?
Chaos.
These are the words they use.
What is number five?
Some form of what?
Atrial or ventricular?
Ventricular.
How do you know it's ventricular?
QRS.
And when it says bizarre, bizarre always applies to tachycardia.
Bizarre is the word they use for tachycardias.
Chaos is the word they use for fibrillations.
Don't get that confused.
Chaos is for fibrillations.
Bizarre is for tachycardia.
So if you put two and two together, what is number five?
T-tach.
Ventricular tachycardia.
Do you see how this can be easy if you just know your words?
Why did they do that?
What's that?
Why did they put chaotic then?
They did do that.
How could we know that?
Oh, why didn't they teach you that?
I mean, why did they put that in the HESI test?
Why did they put those words in there?
They did.
You mean they...
I mean, yeah, why do they?
They are trying to mess this up.
No, actually, what they're doing is they're seeing if you know what those words mean.
You show up and say, do you know what chaos means?
Somewhere along the line, we should have been taught this.
Yes.
Somewhere along the line, you should have been taught that chaos was fifth.
Flutter was sawtooth.
Bizarre was tacky.
QRS was ventricle.
P-wave was atrial.
You show up and say, you should have been taught this.
Wow.
Okay.
Well, what about a periodic wide bizarre QRS?
That's a PVC.
Why is it ventricular?
And why is it wide and bizarre?
Because it's like one snapshot of a tachycardia.
Right?
It's just one piece of tachycardia.
So, is it possible, could you call a salvo of PVCs?
You know, a salvo of them, a group of them in a row, a salvo of them.
What else could you call it?
A short run of V-tac.
Couldn't you?
Because it's the same idea.
Now, let me ask you this.
Do we care, do physicians care about people having PVCs?
Generally speaking, no.
How high a priority is a client with a PVC?
If you had to prioritize four clients and one of them has PVCs,
how high would you prioritize that guy?
Low, moderate, or high?
Low.
All right?
Now, under three circumstances, you could elevate that person to moderate.
Not high priority, just moderate priority.
And here is the list right here below.
If there are more than six PVCs in a minute, or more than six PVCs in a row,
or if the PVC falls on the T-wave of the previous beat, that's called R on T phenomenon,
if one of those is true, you elevate the priority of your PVC client to moderate.
So PVCs never reach what level?
High.
They never reach high.
The most the PVC client can reach is moderate,
and that's if there's more than six in a row, six in a minute, or falling on the T-wave.
Otherwise, how high do you prioritize your PVC patient?
Low.
Is it true that after an MI, after a heart attack, if they're having PVCs, what do you know?
Is that good or bad?
That's good.
So actually, it means they're re-perfusing.
So that doesn't raise their priority.
It even lowers it, because you're doing great.
So anybody ever work coronary care or telemetry?
If you call physicians in the middle of the night to tell them that the patient is having PVCs,
what is the most common order you will receive?
Don't ever call me.
And how will they say that?
Continue.
Discontinue the monitor.
They'll tell you to DC the monitor.
Why?
Because if you don't have the monitor, you can't see the PVCs.
If you don't see the PVCs, you won't call them.
You learn real quick.
Don't call a doctor about PVCs unless you want to lose your monitor.
Okay?
One periodic.
All right.
Period.
Lethal arrhythmias.
How high a priority are these?
Moderate, low, or high?
These are high priority.
There are two of them that are super high priorities.
They're lethal, meaning they will kill you in eight minutes or less.
The first one is a systole.
Right?
If you're a systolic, you've got eight minutes or that brain is gone.
V-fib is also the lethal one.
What do A-systole and V-fib have in common?
No cardiac output.
And if you've got no cardiac output, you do not have brain perfusion.
And if you don't have brain perfusion, you're dead in eight minutes.
So think of your four patients and one of the patients has A-systole or V-fib.
How high do you prioritize that patient?
They're probably number one.
Probably number one.
Letter D.
One of these arrhythmias is a potentially life-threatening.
It is not life-threatening.
It is only potentially life-threatening, but that still makes it a fairly high priority.
And that is ventricular tachycardia, V-tach.
So therefore, what is the difference between V-tach and the A-systole V-fibers?
V-tachers have a cardiac output.
So that makes all the difference in the world.
Were you ever in a code situation and they're given drugs or something, the rhythm changes?
On the monitor, the rhythm changes because of something they did.
What's the first question the doctor will always ask?
What's that?
Do you get a pulse with that?
Why? What are they asking?
Is there a cardiac output with that?
And so even if the rhythm changes to something that looks good, if there's no pulse, there's no cardiac output, it's just as bad as what was there before.
All right.
Turn the page and let's talk about treatment of these problems.
On that number six where periodic is undermined, does periodic mean PBC?
Yes.
Because it's not a continuous phenomenon.
It's only a patient.
Okay. Let's talk about the treatment.
The first two are P, B, C, and V-tach.
They are both ventricular, correct?
See this?
See my fingers?
What letter do they make?
A B.
For ventricular, now watch what happens.
For ventricular, use what letter is that?
L.
Lidocaine.
For ventricular, use lidocaine.
So I just hope you remember that.
Ventricular, lidocaine.
Now I know that lidocaine is not used in a lot of squads now in the bigger cities because they're using amiodarone.
But Bortz is going to talk more about lidocaine.
After April 1, it would be amiodarone.
Amiodarone.
So I guess after April 1, I'm going to have to say, see the B for ventricular?
No, I could get something else.
Why do squads in rural areas still stock lidocaine instead of amiodarone for V-tach?
I mean V-tach and P-C.
Yes, it's like one tenth of a cost to miss four times the shelf length.
So why would you buy a super expensive drug that's going to expire in three weeks when you won't use it that much?
But if you were a squad in Franklin County, you're going to use that up so fast, you might as well have amiodarone.
But if you were in Vinton County or something like that, you'd just lock it.
Amiodarone is going to spoil before you ever use it.
Okay, a superventricular arrhythmias. What's that a synonym for?
Supraventriculars.
Atrials.
For atrial arrhythmias, use the A, B, C, Ds.
Atrial starts with what letter?
A.
So remember the A, B, C, Ds of atrial treatment.
So for ventricular, you use what?
Metrically used, lidocaine. For atrial, use the A, B, C, Ds.
So what are the A, B, C, Ds?
A stands for adenocard.
A, D, E, N, O, C, A, R, D, adenocard.
A, D, E, N, O, C, A, R, D, adeno card.
Which is adenosine.
This is the one you have to push in less than eight seconds.
So is it a fast or slow IV push?
Fast.
Fast. Now, why do I bring that up?
Well, here's why I bring it up.
The reason why I bring it up is when you're talking about IV push,
when you don't know, you go slow.
You've heard that?
When you don't know, you go slow when you're pushing.
Now, I'm worried because you go, oh, I don't know adenocard, so I'm going to what?
Slow.
No.
This is the one you've got to know.
It's the super fast.
You've got eight seconds.
They call it slamming.
Have you ever heard of that?
You've got to slam this drug.
You've got to push it in in eight seconds, and then the other nurse pushes 20 milliliters
of flush right after it.
So you're going wham, and they're going wham.
So you've got to use a big vein.
You can't use one of these.
You have to use what we call the intern vein.
Something so big an intern can hit it.
So you just use the intern vein.
One of those big ones.
Now, the problem with this is when you slam it fast, what could they go into?
Each.
A.
Each out?
A systole.
And they could go into a systole for about 30 seconds, but they'll come out of it.
You just have to trust.
They'll come out of it.
They really will.
It's kind of scary.
You know, 30 seconds of a systole is scary.
But what do you do?
Just sit there, relax.
You're going to be okay.
Now, what's the big thing you have to know with a denim card?
Push it fast, and don't worry about a systole.
Oh, well, that's longer than 30 seconds.
Okay, B. B stands for beta blockers.
Beta blockers.
And what do all beta blockers end in?
L-O-L.
L-O-L. Yes.
They all end in long.
L-O-L.
A-tenolol.
Natalol.
Carvetolol.
Redolol.
Propranolol.
Those are all beta blockers.
This is the best class of drugs, best-named class of drugs in the universe.
Every drug that is a lol is a beta blocker, and every beta blocker is a lol.
It's great.
Every drug should be that way.
I was just going to say, when we were in school, we used to do stupid things.
See that right there?
That's baby beta.
See the little curving here?
Actually, in the figure, it would look like this.
Yeah, that's baby beta, and she's what?
Blocked in.
She can't go either way.
Beta blocking.
So, lol, beta blockers.
Now, beta blockers are negative ino, negative chrono, negative dromo.
Negative ino, negative chrono, negative dromo.
So they're like what?
And so they're like valium for your?
So they'll treat A, AA, and AA.
And what are we talking about here?
AA, anti-atrial arrhythmia.
Correct?
So what will beta blockers have as a side effect?
Headache and hypo attention.
Just like the calcium channel blockers.
So don't make a big difference between calcium channel blockers and beta blockers.
Generally speaking.
The only thing is that calcium channel blockers are better for people with asthma.
Because beta blockers, vaso, I mean bronchitis, so people that have other diseases like COPD
probably should be on a calcium channel.
Although a beta does all the same things and has all the same side effects.
Oh, so therefore what's the C?
Calcium channel blockers.
Because beta blockers and calcium channel blockers are like valium for your heart.
They're negative ino, negative chrono, negative dromo.
They treat A, AA, and AA, and they have the side effects of H and H.
Both of them.
The D stands for digitalis.
Digoxin, lan-ox-in.
You have to know these names because they will only give you one name for this drug.
They'll say lan-ox-in.
You're supposed to know that's digitalis.
They will not give you both.
If you do not know that lan-ox-in is digitalis, you don't know what everybody else knows.
So know it.
So what are the ABCDs of treating atrial arrhythmias?
Adena, beta, calcium, dinge.
Those are the ABCDs of atrial treatments.
So what do you use for ventriculars?
Lidocaine.
What do you use for atrials?
Adena, beta, calcium, dinge.
The ABCDs.
Okay, what do you use, number four, what do you use for V-fib?
It rhymes for V-fib-ud-fib.
For V-fib-ud-fib.
In other words, what's D-fib-me?
Shaka.
And asystole, what do you use for asystole?
Epinephrine and atropine.
In that order, what's the first one you give?
Epinephrine.
Epinephrine, then if that doesn't work, you give?
Atropine.
Now, the way I remember this is, look at the word asystole.
All right?
What's the first letter?
A, which stands for?
Atropine.
What's the last letter?
E, which stands for?
Epinephrine.
But give it reverse.
So A for atropine, E for epinephrine.
What I do is I always do this.
A, sistole, atropine, epinephrine.
You see this visual?
I sort of have this visual of it coming down, and then I just go, give it opposite.
So what do you do for V-fib?
V-fib.
What do you do for V-tac and PBCs?
What do you do for atrial flutter and atrial fibrillation?
Abend, denovative calcium dige.
What do you do for asystole?
Epinephrine.
Epinephrine and?
Atropine.
Very good.
If you know that, you know more than what most people know about those emergency things.
Okay, let's talk about chest tubes.
The purpose of a chest tube is to reestablish negative pressure in the plural space.
Reestablish negative pressure in the plural space.
So the plural space is a place where negative is good.
Because don't we tend to think of negative as bad, but negative is good in your plural space.
Negative makes things stick together.
You got me?
Okay, what's your name?
Shauna.
Here's Shauna.
Okay, Shauna and I are going to demonstrate.
Okay.
Stay off first.
Shauna is the chest wall.
I am the lung.
She is the chest wall, I am the lung.
Now, we're actually three-dimensional, although we're only showing you a one-dimensional picture.
There's actually, you know, we're, you know what I'm saying?
Everybody gets a cross-section here we're looking at.
Okay, so she's the what?
I'm the lung.
Okay, what's that here?
Atmosphere care.
Right.
So this is skin and bones and muscles, right?
And then I'm a what?
Lung and what's in here?
A what?
The alveolus.
I can't take three of us.
I know you're used to a picture with three, but I can't do that.
Okay, that's the alveolus.
Are you sitting in the picture?
Now, on the inside of the chest wall is a lining called the visceral, I mean the parietal pleura.
So this is the what?
Parietal pleura.
It lines the inside of the chest wall.
Okay, now on the outside of me there's another lining.
What's this called?
Visceral pleura.
Visceral pleura and it lines the outside of the lung.
Between the...
Chest wall.
Parietal pleura and the visceral pleura is the...
Plural space.
So we got this space here called the what?
Now, what kind of pressure should be in there?
Negative pressure.
Now, what does negative pressure do to things?
Pull them together or push them apart?
Negative.
Pull them together like a vacuum.
Positive pressure pushes things away.
So, what are we going to do here?
There's negative pressure in here.
What's going to happen?
We're stuck together because there's blood.
Negative pressure in the full space.
Now, how is this going to work?
Okay, we're going to breathe in.
Now, when we breathe in the chest wall expands outward.
Okay, so we're going to take the steps out that way.
So, now we're going to breathe in and you watch the air.
Air going into the what?
Now, here's the air.
Now, ready?
Let's breathe in.
What happened to the air?
Okay, now let's breathe out.
Just breathe in and in.
Let's breathe out again.
Alright, now there's a good what?
Air is changed because of theirs.
Negative pressure.
And I'll take your gun and shoot us.
Just get started.
Now, what has entered the full space?
Air and blood creating what?
A muscle person, which is going to do what to us?
Part.
Okay, now I want you, so we're no longer what?
Stuck together.
She has muscles.
What don't I have?
Muscles.
She does the work of breathing.
I just hang along for the ride.
Now, what we're going to do is now that there's positive pressure in here,
I want Shana to breathe in and then breathe out.
And I want you to watch what happens to the air exchange.
Okay, breathe in.
Breathe out.
Breathe in.
What happened?
She's doing a lot of work.
But there's no air exchange because there's
a lot of pressure in the...
Okay, now take that chest tube you have there in your hand.
You know, pretend you're sticking it in here.
Okay?
Now give me some suction.
Okay, now what did we just do?
Breathe.
Re-established.
Negative pressure in the whole space.
So now she can breathe in.
And breathe out.
Now we heal.
And what does she do?
Pulls out the tube and we're good to go.
Thank you.
Very good.
So, she's going to be in the bathroom now.
So what's the purpose of a chest tube?
Re-established.
Negative pressure in the whole space.
So that the lung expands when the chest wall moves.
Is that making sense?
Why you need that tube in there?
Okay.
Now when you get a chest tube question, look at the reason for which it was placed.
Letter A there, number one says, you know, in a pneumothorax the chest tube removes what?
Air.
Pneumo means air.
So in a pneumothorax, what created the positive pressure?
Air.
So I've got to put a chest tube in to remove air so I can re-establish the negative pressure.
Okay.
But in a pneumothorax the chest tube removes blood because what's causing the positive
pressure?
Blood.
And I've got to remove it to re-establish the negative pressure.
And in a pneumothorax what's in the floral space?
Air.
Air and blood and I must remove both air and blood to re-establish the negative pressure
in the floral space.
So if Bors gives you a question and says that you have a patient with pneumo, with chest
tubes in for a hemothorax, what would you report to nurse LPS or doctor R.S.?
What would you report to the nurse or the doctor?
Number one, the chest tube is not bubbling.
Two, the chest tube drained 800 ml in first 10 hours.
The chest tube is not draining.
The chest tube is intermittently bubbling.
Well, you have to say to yourself, what do I expect from a hemo?
What does a hemo chest tube put in for a hemothorax?
What's it supposed to do?
Drain what?
Blood.
So which one of these says it is not doing what it is supposed to do?
Number three.
So which one would you report to the nurse or the physician?
Because it is not doing what it is supposed to do.
Do you see what I'm saying?
Well, what if I said this?
Pneumothorax.
What would you report to the physician?
Well, you could have two of them.
What would they be?
One or two.
Right?
What's wrong with one?
It needs to bubble.
It's not doing what it's supposed to do.
What's wrong with two?
It's doing something it's not supposed to do.
And in that case, it would be a hard, you see what I'm saying, it would be a hard one to do.
But the point is, is that do you see how that it definitely wasn't number three.
Do you see when I changed?
Did you see that when I changed from a hemo to a pneumo, what was the right answer is no longer even an option for the right answer.
So if you're going to get chest tube questions correct, what must you pay particularly attention to?
Particularly attention to.
The disease for which it was placed.
And that will tell you what you should expect.
Does that make sense that you're going to have to watch that?
Otherwise, you wouldn't get it right.
Okay, the other thing you have to pay attention to is letter B, the location of the tubes.
The location of the tubes.
And the two locations are apical, A-P-I-C-A-L, and basilar, B-A-S-I-L-A-R.
Apical, number one is apical, A-P-I-C-A-L.
And number two is basilar, B-A-S-I-L-A-R.
Apical and basilar.
Now apical means the chest tube is way up high.
And if you put a chest tube way up high, what are you going to remove?
Air, because air rises.
So apical is remove air.
Basilar are at the bottom of the lungs, so they will remove what?
Blood, because blood is subject to gravity.
So apical is remove air.
Basilar is remove blood.
A for A, B for B. What do I mean by that?
A for cold starts with A, and that removes air, which starts with A.
And basilar starts with B, and it should remove blood.
So if they say your apical chest tube is draining 300 milliliters per hour,
your apical is draining 300 per hour, what do you think?
Good or bad?
Your basilar is draining 200 mils per hour.
Fine.
It needs to come out.
Now, your apical tube is not bubbling.
Your apical tube is bubbling.
Your basilar tube is not bubbling.
Fine. Your basilar tube is bubbling.
Why?
You know what I'm saying?
So do you see where location depends?
So what will they put in for a hemo?
What will they put in for a pneumo?
And what will they put in for a pneumo-hemo?
One of each.
Which brings up the next three questions.
Examples.
How many chest tubes and where would you place them for unilateral pneumo-hemo thorax?
Unilateral pneumo-hemo.
Two.
You'd use an apical for the pneumo and a basilar for the hemo.
B. How many chest tubes and where for a bilateral pneumo?
Again, how many?
Two.
But what would they both be?
Apical.
So you'd use an apical on the right and an apical on the left.
Then let her see how many chest tubes and where would you place them for post-op chest surgery?
Two.
Here again, two.
An apical and a basilar on the side of the surgery.
Because you are to assume, you are to assume,
that chest surgery or trauma is unilateral unless otherwise specified.
So if they just said he had chest trauma, would you assume it's unilateral or bilateral?
Unilateral.
Chest surgery.
Unilateral or bilateral?
Unilateral.
You always assume unilaterality.
Never assume that it's bilateral.
So the only time you're taking care of bilateral is when they say bilateral.
All right?
Oh, there's a trick question though about chest tubes.
How many chest tubes would you need and where would you place them for a post-op right pneumonectomy?
None.
Why?
They give a point now.
Pneumonectomy means removal of the what?
Whole lung.
There's no lung.
There's no plural space.
There's nothing.
So if there's no plural space, why do you want to reestablish pressure in something that does not exist?
Correct?
So you do not use chest tubes for pneumonectomies.
You use them for lobectomies, wedge resections, those kinds of things.
All right.
Turn the page.
Let's talk about troubleshooting.
Do you guys remember seeing closed chest drainage devices like a thorvac, thorvac, pneumonvac, Emerson?
And there are those plastic containers that the tube is connected to.
Well, what do you do if you knock that over?
I mean, you didn't break it.
You just knocked it over.
What do you do?
Set it back up.
Set it back up and take some deep breaths.
Is it a medical emergency?
Does the physician need call?
Does the RN need notifying?
Do you need to do anything other than have them take a couple deep breaths?
No.
It is no big deal.
Do you understand that?
So do not get all up tight when you knock over that device.
But number two, what do you do if the water still breaks?
The actual device, that device breaks.
Now, is that the same thing as we were just talking about?
Or is this something totally different?
Totally different because now positive pressure can get in the floral space.
So what do we do?
We'll see you break it.
What do you do?
Clamp it.
That's the first thing you do is clamp it.
Why?
So nothing gets in.
Then what do you do next?
Well, there's a couple of steps they're going to put in between there.
Clamp it.
Put it in sterile water.
There's a step before that.
That's the third step.
Clamp it.
It's too obvious.
Cut it away from the broken device.
Take your scissors and cut that tube away from that broken device
because it's no good anymore, right?
So cut it all away.
Then what do you do to the end of that tube then that's been cut away?
You put it in the back here.
Stick that end of that tube under sterile water.
Now what are you going to do next?
Unclamp it.
Why unclamp it?
Because now you've reestablished the water seal.
You understand it doesn't need clamps as long as it's underwater.
And it's better to be underwater than to be clamped.
Why is it better to be underwater, the end of the tube, underwater,
than for the tube to be clamped?
Why is it better?
Sterile.
No, not sterile necessary.
Necessarily.
Air can't go in, but stuff can come out.
If it's clamped, what's the problem?
Nothing can go in or out.
And you want stuff to come out.
You don't want stuff to go in.
So clamping is only a stop-gap measure.
It doesn't solve the problem.
What solves the problem?
Sticking the tube underwater.
So what is the order?
If they gave you a click and drag when the water seal breaks,
what would be the person who would click and drag?
Clamp, then what?
Cut, then submerge, then unclamp.
It's alphabetic cold.
Clamp, cut, submerge, unclamp.
That is your order.
So if they said to you, what is the first thing you're going to do
when the water seal breaks?
The first thing?
What will you pick?
Submerge the end of the tube underwater or clamp the tube?
Clamp.
Because when they say first, they're asking about what?
Order.
Right?
But what if they say this?
They ask you the exact same question with the exact same answers
and they change one word in the question.
The word they change is from first to best.
And they say, what is the best thing to do when the water seal breaks?
What is now the answer?
Submergent under?
!
The tube under?
The end of the tube underwater.
Why is it the best?
Is it actually solves the problem by reestablishing the water seal?
The clamping was only what?
A temporary fix.
It's not the best, it's the first, but it's not the best.
So do you understand that a best question is different than a first question?
Very different.
A first question is asking you all about order.
A best question is asking you what's the one thing you would do
if you could only do one of these?
So if you could only do one, clamp it and nothing else
or put it under the end of the tube underwater and nothing else,
which one would you do if you could only do one?
Submerge.
So it's what?
Best.
Because what's the best answer?
The one that you would do if you could only do one.
What's the first one?
The one you do first.
And that may be the same and it may be different,
but a lot of people screw up questions because they're answering firsts
instead of bests or bests instead of firsts.
And they're not paying attention to what the question is asking.
For example, and this is really important to get
because people have trouble with this.
You notice a person has ventricular fibrillation on the modern.
V-fib, good or bad?
Bad.
No cardiac output.
You run to the room, they're not responsive and they don't have a pulse.
What's the first thing you're going to do?
A, place a backboard.
B, begin chest compressions.
Now, first is about what?
Order.
So you're between those two, right?
So if you pick place backboard, what are you saying?
I'm going to place the backboard first, then I'm going to start chest compressions.
If you pick chest compressions, what do you say?
I'm going to start chest compressions, then I'm going to place the backboard.
Well, what would it be better to do first?
Place the backboard.
And remember, it's a perfect world, so where's the backboard?
Right there.
Boom, it's there.
So say, well, it could take 10 minutes for somebody else to bring the code.
No, it's a perfect world, it's there.
Okay?
So what's the first thing you do?
Place the backboard or begin chest compressions?
Place the backboard.
But what if I say this?
Person has V-fib, they're unresponsive, no pulse.
What's the best thing to do?
Place the backboard or begin chest compressions.
Well, if you do one of those, you don't get to do the other one.
You understand?
In a best question, how many things do you get to do?
One.
If you do one, you don't get to do the other one.
So if you pick backboard as the best, what are you saying you're going to do?
I'm going to roll them over, put them on the backboard, and go, oh, okay, now.
Let's go and get the pulse.
Hopefully somebody will come along before eight minutes.
But if you pick chest compressions, what are you saying?
If you want to do chest compressions while they're on the floor, they get no backboard.
Well, would you rather do chest compressions without a backboard or a backboard without chest compressions?
Which one's best?
The chest compressions.
Which one's first?
The backboard.
Are you getting this first versus best?
We're going to talk a lot about this in the next three days so you get good at this.
Most people don't even catch the difference.
No, not you guys.
Well, a lot of you.
Number two, what do you do if the chest tube gets pulled out?
Have you ever seen that?
I haven't seen it.
Yeah, I did.
I worked Southwest Nine, and when St. East was open in Dayton, Ohio, I had worked in the intensive care unit from the Open Hearts,
and they had these chest tubes in there.
Well, this guy's huge.
He's like 10 times to my size.
Well, that's not hard to beat, but he was really big.
And I knew that I had to get him in bed, and I had one chance.
Otherwise, we're both going down.
And I had to do it all in one motion.
So I got there like this, you know, wide stance of the bed is here, he's here.
I got the belt, and I think, okay, now.
And I thought, oh, your stance isn't wide enough.
So I went.
And when I went like that, I stepped on his chest tube.
Oh, no.
And I did not know it.
And I went, okay.
One, two, three.
He's flipping him up, and out came this, because I'm standing on it.
I got pulled out, but I didn't know it.
And so he's there, and he's talking and whatnot.
And I'm going, there's a blood on my pants.
I said, blood all over.
I'm like, what's this?
Here's the chest tube lying on the floor.
So I'm going, oh, great.
But he says, oh, I feel pretty good.
I feel a lot better now.
Let's talk to the other ones.
But what's the first thing you do?
What do you think the first thing you do is?
Take a gloved hand and cover the hole.
What's the best thing to do?
Cover it with Vaseline gauze.
So what's the first thing you do?
Cover it with your gloved hand.
What's the best thing to do?
Vaseline gauze.
Because if you get, they say you accidentally pulled out the chest tube.
What's the best thing to do?
Best thing.
And you're between, cover it with your gloved hand versus Vaseline gauze.
If you pick, cover it with your gloved hand, what are you saying?
I'm going to cover it with my gloved hand and that's all I'm going to do.
So you're going to follow them around all day long with the gloved hand.
No, you're going to put a Vaseline in it.
That actually solves the problem.
Do you see the difference?
But if they ask first, you're going to put a gloved hand, then Vaseline gauze.
But best thing, Vaseline gauze, forget about the gloved hand.
Are you seeing this difference?
It's real important.
Real critical that you see this.
Bubbling.
They love to ask about bubbling chest tubes.
You've seen these questions around?
Yeah.
Okay, ask yourself two questions.
Where is it bubbling and when is it bubbling?
If you do not ask yourself those two questions, you're going to get it wrong.
You can get this question right if you ask where and when.
Because it is going to depend on where and when.
Because sometimes bubbling is good and sometimes it's bad.
It depends on where and when.
So let's talk about it.
If I say bubbling, bubbling, bubbling, what do you say?
Where?
I say water seal.
You see where I'm at?
Then what do you ask me?
And I say intermittent.
Is everybody where I'm at?
So intermittent bubbling in the water seal is good.
Document it.
It's never bad.
It's always good.
Document it.
Okay, I say bubbling, bubbling.
You say what?
I say water seal.
You say, I say continuous.
This is bad.
There is a leak.
You do not want continuous bubbling in the water seal.
That means there's a leak in the system.
You've got to find it and tape it.
Put tape over it until it stops leaking.
LPS, this is perfectly within the scope of your practice to put tape on these things.
And stop the continuous bubbling.
I say bubbling, bubbling, bubbling.
You say what?
Where?
I say suction control chamber.
You say, and I say intermittent.
That's bad.
The suction is not high enough in that case.
If you're only getting intermittent bubbling in the suction control,
your suction is too low.
You've got to go to the wall.
You know what I mean by the wall?
You have that dial at the wall.
You've got to turn it up until what happens?
Bubbles how?
Continuous.
Because if I say bubbling, bubbling, you say,
where?
I say suction control.
You say, and I say continuous.
That is good.
You document that.
So, two scenarios are good and two scenarios are bad.
Did you notice that?
And what did you notice about the two chambers?
They're opposite.
What's good in one is bad in the other.
Now, I do not memorize all four of those.
I don't.
I memorize one.
And then I deduce all the other three.
The one that makes the most intuitive sense to me is this.
Think about this.
If something is sealed, which chamber am I talking about?
If something is sealed, should you have a continuous bubble?
No.
That means it's what?
We're leaking.
So that is bad.
So intermittent in the seal is and the suction control is the opposite of that.
Because this just makes sense to me.
If this were a two liter bottle of pop and it was on the grocery store shelf
and it was sitting there going bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble.
Bubbling how?
Continuously.
Would you buy it?
No.
What's your conclusion about it?
The what?
Seal is broken.
In life, when things bubble continuously, you think, oh, the seal's broken.
Well, in a chest tube, if it's bubbling continuously, the water seal is broken.
And so that's bad.
Do you see how I want you to remember it?
Did you ever notice that when you do chest tube questions, that it's so frustrating because sometimes you're saying,
bubbling is bad, sometimes you're saying, and they say, no, it's okay.
And then the next time you say, oh, it's okay.
And then they say, no, it's bad.
And then the next time you say, oh, it must be bad.
And then they say, no, it's okay.
And you're going, just make up your mind.
Is bubbling good or bad?
And what's the answer?
It's both. It depends.
And that's what you're not picking up.
You never have, you have made all chest tubes the same.
Right?
Yeah.
It's a very different.
See, my philosophy is make something simple if it's simple, but don't oversimplify if it's actually more involved.
So hopefully that will help you with your chest tube questions to know when bubbling's okay and when bubbling's not okay and when draining's okay and when draining's not okay and what the purpose of it is.
If any of you like analogies, learn my analogy.
Dog is to meow, as bark is to cat.
You know that you're not good at analogies when I say meow is to cat as bark is to, and you say tree.
You know, you're not very good at that, you know.
But here's an analogy that might help you.
A straight catheter, got where I'm at?
A straight catheter is to a Foley catheter as a Thoracentesis is to a chest tube.
Did you get the analogy?
Because what's a straight catheter?
In and out.
What's a Foley?
In secure drain in.
Keep continuing with strain.
What's a Thoracentesis?
In and out to reestablish negative pressure.
What's a chest tube?
Stick it in, secure it, leave it in.
So do you see the point?
So just think of a Thoracentesis as an in and out chest tube.
And that will help you answer questions there too.
So which one has a higher risk of infection?
Thoracentesis or chest tube?
Because what has a higher risk of infection?
A straight catheter or Foley?
Right?
Same idea.
Rules for clamping tubes.
Never clamp a tube for longer than 15 seconds without a doctor's order.
You're not allowed to clamp chest tubes for longer than 15 seconds without a doctor's order.
So if you break the water seal, what is the first thing you do?
Break the water seal.
First thing.
Now, how long do you have to get that thing cut off and underwater?
15 seconds or you've got to what?
Unclamp.
So have those sterile water bottles nearby.
It drives me crazy.
When I work as a nurse and I get people in chest tubes,
I go into the room and guess what's all over the walls and all over the bed table and everywhere?
Clamps.
I can put like six clamps in every room.
What can I not find within 100 yards of sterile water?
Which one can I simulate and don't need?
A clamp because I can kink the tube off with my fingers.
What can I not simulate?
Cerroan.
Where's your coat?
Where's your coat going?
Number two, use rubber-tipped double clamps.
Use rubber-tipped double clamps.
In other words, if you've got to clamp something, what should they be covered with?
The teeth.
Rubber.
Why should the teeth of the clamp be covered with rubber?
Because otherwise you're going to puncture it.
That's covered.
And why double clamps?
Why two?
Because we're nurses.
Okay.
There's no research-based evidence to prove that two clamps is better than one.
It's just the way we are.
Okay.
Okay, a genital-hard defense.
And then we'll do some real brief ones that will be done for the day.
Con, genital, heart, knee-bend.
Everybody knows what congenital heart defects are?
Every congenital heart defect is either trouble or no trouble.
What I mean by that is either a congenital heart defect causes a lot of problems or it's no big deal at all.
There is no in-between defense.
It's kind of bad but kind of good.
It's either what?
All bad or all good.
It's either all bad, all good, nothing in between.
They're either what?
Trouble or they are no trouble.
Now, to memorize congenital heart, I want you to memorize one word and only one word and that word is trouble.
Now, you notice it has seven letters.
You notice that shaded box has seven blanks.
I want you to write the word trouble in there but capitalize the consonants, keep the vowels small and lower case.
Capital T, capital R, small o, small u, capital B, capital L, small e.
Now, all congenital heart defects are what?
Trouble or not.
So what's the big word you have to memorize for congenital heart?
Trouble.
Okay, now if you memorize that, how many of that already memorized?
You memorize it in the last 10 seconds.
Okay, you can repeat that.
You now know 95% of all congenital heart defects.
How do I know that?
Here's how I know it.
If a congenital heart defect is trouble, let's say you guys have trouble defects.
Does logic say you need or don't need surgery?
If they're trouble.
When?
In order to what?
Live.
Okay, if you guys have a no trouble defect, do you need surgery?
No.
Might you have it?
Possibly when?
Years later, if it causes a trouble, but we don't expect it to cause any trouble because
it's not trouble.
Okay, well, you guys have a trouble defect.
What is your growth and development?
Slow, delayed.
Why?
Because you have a defect, which is?
Trouble.
What is your growth and development?
Why normal?
Because your defect is no trouble.
What's your life expectancy?
Normal because it's no trouble.
What's you guys' life expectancy?
Short because it's trouble.
What are your parents experiencing a lot of?
Stress, grief, financial, all kinds of caregiver issues.
What about your parents?
No more problems than the average person on the street.
Do you go home on an apnea monitor?
No, why?
Because it's not trouble.
Do you go home on an apnea monitor?
Yeah.
Because you have what?
Trouble.
How long do you stay in the hospital after you're born?
Long time.
Weeks.
How long do you stay?
Twenty-four hours.
Thirty-six hours and you're gone.
Why?
Because it's no trouble.
Who follows your care?
What medical professional follows your care?
Which doctor?
What kind of doctor?
Pediatrician.
Pediatrician or a nurse practitioner, pediatric nurse practitioner, right?
Who could follow you guys?
Who would follow you?
Pediatric cardiologist.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
So if it's trouble, make it trouble.
And if it's no trouble, don't make it.
See, because the way they'll ask this question is they'll say,
you are teaching the parents of a child born with tetralogy of fallot,
what will you teach them?
And it will say, this decreases life expectancy.
Do you see what I'm saying?
Or it'll say, it's just fine, it's no problem.
Well, which one do you pick?
Well, it depends on whether it's what?
Trouble.
Trouble or not.
If it's no trouble, what do you tell the parents?
Big deal.
If it's trouble, what do you tell the parents?
Whoa, not good.
Now, boards will not give you pictures of defects and ask you what they are.
Why?
That's not your job.
You don't make the diagnosis the radiologist does.
What do you do?
What's your role in congenital heart defect?
Teaching the parents the implications.
And if that's your job, if it's trouble,
teach them things that it's going to be a lot of trouble.
And if it's no trouble, pick the answer that says, this is no trouble.
Do you see where you're going to be able to pick the answer out?
How many agree you'll be able to know what to teach the parents
as long as you know whether it's what?
Trouble or not, correct?
Okay, now the other thing about trouble is,
they always want to know, does the defect shunt blood right to left or left to right?
Remember that?
How many remember left to right, right to left shunt?
Okay.
Look in the word trouble.
Look at the way it is spelled.
Is there any help for us in remembering which way trouble defects shunt blood?
Right to left.
Why did you say right to left?
Because r comes before l in the word trouble.
Trouble.
So a trouble defect is right to left.
Why?
Why is a trouble defect right to left?
Something somebody said, because it recirculates diastole to left.
No, because that's the way it's spelled.
It's too late for me to teach you all this stuff.
If something can be simple, let's make it what?
Simple.
And I am not teaching you the word tolerber.
I am teaching you the word what?
Travola.
And in the word trouble, what comes first?
R.
R then l.
So trouble defects are right to left because trouble is spelled that way.
So what way are no trouble defects shunt blood?
Left.
Left, right, because that's not the way trouble is spelled because it's not trouble.
So if a kid has a right to left shunt, what do you tell the parents about surgery?
Kid has a right to left shunt.
What do you tell the parents?
Right to left.
So it must be trouble.
So I'm telling the parents what we have.
Okay, what if a kid has a left to right shunt?
What do you tell the parents about the growth and development?
Left to right.
That's not the way trouble is spelled, so it cannot be trouble.
So we say normal.
Are you getting this?
Okay, the other thing they want to know is is the kid cyanotic or asyanotic?
Remember that?
Cyanotic.
Asyanotic.
What does cyanotic mean?
Blue.
Anything that can help us with that?
B.
B, the word B, the letter B in trouble.
See, we're using the consonants.
We're not going to use the vowels.
I'm just going to use the consonants here.
So B means blue.
So what types of shunts are blue?
What types of shunts are blue?
Right to left means blue.
So left to right means not blue, which is pink, A cyanotic.
Do you got me?
So why are right to left blue?
It's trouble.
Because trouble is spelled that way.
Yes.
Don't talk to me about deoxygenated blood.
I don't care.
I just want to know, can you do this?
Okay, now, what do you know about a congenital heart attack?
If you know it is trouble, start listing the things you know about.
If it is trouble, what do you know?
Chose blood.
What?
Right to left.
Cyanotic.
Need.
Perseverance.
Delayed.
Decreased.
Liveness expectancy.
Needs.
Pediatric.
Perseverance.
Exercise intolerance.
Needs the meds.
Needs the apnea monitors.
It's going to stay longer.
Parental guilt.
Financial difficulties.
Caregiver stress.
Right?
Because it's what?
Trouble.
But if it's no trouble, what do you tell the parents?
No trouble.
You know it's left to right.
You know it's blue.
You know it's no big deal.
So with troubles you go, whoa.
With no troubles you go, ahh.
Right?
Now, there are 40 some congenital heart defects, correct?
Some of them are trouble and some of them are not.
How do you remember which ones are trouble?
Well, just memorize them, right?
Memorize them.
Which ones are trouble, correct?
And then you'll know which ones are and the others are no trouble, right?
No.
Because I told you to memorize what?
One word and that would be trouble.
And that would be memorizing more than a word, wouldn't it?
You'd be memorizing a list.
Well, what consonant have we not yet used?
T.
What position does T hold in the word trouble?
First.
It just so happens why total sheer courage is so important.
So, what's the number of consonants?
T.
with ventricular septal defect. What is it? Why? It starts with a B, that's not a T, so
it's not, so it shuts blood from the left or right kid is. A. Son, I can tell the parents,
don't worry about it. Okay, your kid has tetralogy of phthalo, that starts with a what? It starts
with a what? T and that means it's. Trouble. Trouble, it shuts blood. Right and left kid
is. Son, I can tell the parents. Okay, patent, ductus arteriosus. That starts with the letter
P, that's not a, so it's not, so it shuts blood. Left or right kid is? Pink, can you
tell the parents? Okay, patent for rheumun ovale. Starts with a P, that's not a, so it's
not, so you tell the parents, truncus arteriosus. Starts with a P and that means it, so it shuts
blood from the, the kid is. Blue, can you tell the parents? Not good. Transposition of the
great vessels. Trouble. Tricuspid atresia. Atrial septal defect. Pulmonic stenosis. Totally
anomalous pulmonary vasculature, TAPV. Do you know what it is? Do I care? No, they don't
care what it is. They want to know what you tell the parents. And since it starts with
a T, you're going to say what? Oh, surgery. Right? Okay, now there's only one exception
to this rule and only those of you from Columbus know it. Those of you from not Columbus don't
hear it because Columbus is a nationwide center for the treatment of these children. It is
a research place for left ventricular hypoplastic syndrome, which you don't, if this were a
class in Cincinnati, no one would know it. How many have heard of it? Raise your hand.
Now that is shocking for a Columbus. Well, how many of you are actually Columbus? Colombians.
Okay. Well, I'm surprised you haven't heard about it, but BORDS will never bring up what?
Left ventricular hypoplastic syndrome because it's like one tenth of one percent of the
whole congenital heart defect. They're going to bring up those more popular ones. You see
what I'm saying? So for BORDS, if it starts with T, it's what? If it does start with T,
it's... So are you going to memorize your defects? No. Just the word trouble. So that
will save you some time, won't it? So that whole chapter you got. Now there's just two
more, couple more things you need to know. All congenital heart defect kids will have
two things whether trouble or not. Number one, they'll all have a murmur. Why do they
all have murmers? Because they're shunted to the blood. They're either shunting from the left
to the right or the right to the left. It really doesn't matter. You're going to hear a murmur.
What I don't want you to think is, oh, only troubles have murmers. And no troubles don't
have murmers. No, no, no. They all have a murmur. You got that? And they all have an
echocardiogram done. Because they've got to find out why. So even your no trouble kids
will have an echocardiogram done. The last thing about congenital heart defects is you
need to know the four defects of tetralogy of phthalo. The four defects of tetralogy
of phthalo. Now, I have been working for 20 years to come up with a good way to remember
these and I haven't come up with a good way. I've come up with an okay way. If anybody
knows a good way, let me know. Okay. The best way I know is the saying, varied pictures
of a ranch. Imagine you went out west to a dude ranch and you have all these pictures
on your cell phone. You have varied pictures of a ranch. Well, what I did with these is,
do you see the word varied? What did I do with it? Capitalize what letters? The first
and last pictures. What did I capitalize? First and last of a, first and last ranch.
First and last. Well, do you know what? V-D-P-S-O-A-R-H-R. Those are the initials of the four defects.
So varied becomes V-D, which is V-D. What would V-D stand for in the heart? Ventricular
defect. What would P-S stand for in the heart? Pulmonary stenosis. Exactly. What would O-A
stand for in the heart? Overriding aorta. Overriding aorta. And what would the R-H stand
for? Right hypertrophy. So here's the good news, everybody. You don't have to recall
these. You just have to recognize them. What is the difference between recall and recognition?
What's recall? Remember it from nothing. What's recognized? Spot it when you see it. So here's
the deal. All you need to do is, and the way they'll do this is they'll say, your patient
has tetralogy of fellow, select all the defects that apply. So you're going to pick out a
what? A V-D, a P-S, an O-A, and an R-H. You just know what I'm saying? And you don't really
have to memorize even what they are. Just a V-D, a P-S, an O-A, and an R-H. Varied pictures
of our ranch. And they don't know about this, so they don't have like two V-D's, two P-S's,
two R-H's. You see what I'm saying? So you should be okay with that. Now does anybody
have a better one? The only one I saw that was kind of interesting, and it is kind of
timely given the time of year we're talking about, is they wanted to get the V-D, P-S,
O-A, R-H, but they wanted it to have something to do with heart because that one has nothing
to do with heart. So they said Valentine's starts with a what? Day. Starts with a what?
B. Pick someone out a red heart. H. Valentine's Day, pick someone out a red heart. V-D, P-S,
O-A, R-H. So I don't care what you do, but I suggest you remember V-D, P-S, O-A, R-H.
But Varied pictures of our ranch does it for me because I always mess up, I always go Valentine's
Day, pick out someone, pick someone out a... So it's kind of sloppy, but I have to tell
you that because that's on there all the time. What are the four defects of tetralogy up
below? It's the only defect where they ask you what it is. So what do you have to memorize
to know all of your congenital heart defects? Trouble and V-D, P-S, O-A, R-H. And you should
get the whole chapter. All right, just in conclusion, I want to do a couple of things
so that you know where we're headed and do short things. Page number 32, infectious disease
and transmission-based precautions. Infectious disease and transmission-based precautions.
Page 32, it's one phase I want to do it right now. There are four transmission-based precautions.
Standard, universal, contact, droplet, and airborne. Which one did I leave out? I don't
know. Standard, universal, walk. I'm assuming you know that. You don't know that. I don't
want you to pass. So the ones you probably need help with are droplet, contact, and airborne.
So let's talk about it. Contact isolation. It is for anything enteric. Enteric, which
means what? Can be caught from intestinal, fecal, or fecal, or. So that would be C. diff,
Clostridium difficile, remember that one? Hepatitis A would be there. That's intestinal.
Any of those cholera, dysentery, you know those ones where the bud's in the diarrhea
and you don't wash your hands and then you touch somebody and then they eat their food.
Sometimes people get confused at hepatitis A and hepatitis B. Which one's which? I always
say hepatitis A stands for anus. I mean it doesn't. But which is the
don't know. Hepatitis A, think hepatitis anus, which tells you it's what? Fecal, oral.
Hepatitis B is hepatitis blood. So it's by the blood. Question?
Anything what? Anything with a vowel comes from the vowel. What do they mean by that?
Oh, okay. The types of hepatitis, anything with a vowel comes from the vowel. Whereas
anything that isn't a vowel comes from blood and volume. That's an interesting one. But
they don't ask you. They just talk about hepatitis A. Okay. Really, that's all they touch.
All right. The other thing they, the other one you use for context is staph infections.
Staph. S-T-A-P-H. Not S-T-A-F-F. These are staph infections. S-T-A-P-H. Staph infections.
And RSV. RSV. Does anybody know what RSV is?
That's the story of that thing the babies use.
Yes, it's the one that the little one and two year olds get with bronchiolitis. It's
no danger to us, but to them it can be fatal. Respiratory syncytial virus. RSV. They will
give you both names. Now, the interesting thing about RSV is how is it transmitted?
Droplet. But what precautions is it on? Contact. See, there's where you don't get confused
on this. You put RSVs on contact precautions even though it is transmitted via droplet.
Because with little kids, they catch it from touching other things that other kids touch
and put in their mouth. It's not because they're sneezing on each other. So you can put them
on droplet and it still would pass. See, what they did is they used to put RSV on droplet,
but it was still going all over the place because they weren't... It was by the contact
with objects that it was passing. So when they put them on contact, it stopped being
passed even though it's transmitted via droplets. Is that ever going to make sense? So how's
RSV usually transmitted? Kid takes a toy, you know, puts it down, next kid takes the
toy and then they get it. So contact works best even though it's transmitted via droplets.
So don't get confused there. It is transmitted droplet, but it's on contact precautions.
And herpes infections. So enterics, staph, RSV, and herpes. These infections are contact
isolation. Now, what is in TEO? What is involved in contact isolation? Now, I'm going to give
you all the latest, newest things because they're really up to on this. So this may
have changed if you've come to another review. So you need to make sure if you're refreshing
that you get this down. All right? Because some things have changed. So, what's going
on? All right? Because some things have changed. In contact, they are now saying private room
is preferred. So therefore, while it is not required, it is preferred, therefore you would
say yes to the private room. Do you understand? So that's a change. Yes to the private room
because it is preferred. However, these kids can be put in the same room as long as you
have a cohort. What does cohort mean? Same. So if you've got two RSV kids, can you put
them in the same room? Yes, but otherwise an RSV needs to be in their own room. Somebody
said, well, it's Cincinnati Children's. We put them all in the same room. Yeah, you're
putting six RSV kids in the same room. Go at it. That's gold. What about an RSV kid
with a suspected RSV kid? Yes or no? No. They have to be cultured and positive before you
can put them in the same room, before you can cohort. So cohorting is done on the basis
of culture or symptom. Culture. Culture, not symptom. Do you understand that? Math, no.
Gloves, yes. Down, yes. Hand washing, when's that ever wrong? Yes. Eye face shields, no.
Not unless you need them for universal, right? Because you don't need them specifically for
this. Special filter mask, no. Patient wear mask, no. Disposable supplies, dedicated equipment,
yes. What is the difference between a disposable supply versus a dedicated equipment? Give
me an example of a disposable supply. Pressure cuff. What's that? It's like pressure cuff.
No, we don't throw the pressure cuff away. Do we throw the thermometer away? Yeah. Like
I was thinking of paper play, a plastic utensil. What is the dedicated equipment? Stethoscope,
a blood pressure cuff that stays only in their rooms. So what are the toys with these kids?
If it's a kid, what's the toy? Disposable or dedicated? Dedicated. Only they play with
them, no other kid plays with them. Of course the two respiratory syncytial virus kids can
play with it, why? Together. Negative air flow, no. No. No. No. No. No. No. No. No. No.
Okay, droplet. Droplet is for bugs that travel three feet on large particles due to sneezing
and coughing. They are for meningituses, all meningitis, and H-flu. Have you heard of H-flu?
Homophilus influenza B? H-flu? What's the big bad disease that H-flu causes? Does anybody
know which one it is? It can, but it's more likely to cause epiglottitis. You're right,
H-flu meningitis is common, but H-flu causes epiglottitis more. Remember that airway disease,
if you stick something down their throat they're going to obstruct so you don't look down their
throat or mess with their throat. So what do you do? Here's another change. Private
room is preferred. Not required, but it is preferred so on boards you would select private
room. It is preferred, unless you are what? Cohort. Based on? Culture. Culture. And if
it is meningitis, what do they all have to have? Lumbar punctures, right? Because that's
where you culture the meningitis. Private room is preferred. Mask? Yes. Gloves? Yes. Gown?
No. You don't need the gown. Hand washing? No. You don't need the gown. Hand washing?
Yes. Special eye face shields? No. Not unless you're doing something for universal. Special
filter mask? No. Patient wear mask when leaving room? Yes. Disposable supplies, dedicated
equipment? What do you think? Yes. And negative airflow? No. Airborne. Airborne is for measles,
mumps, rubella, tuberculosis, and varicella chickenpox. Now, private room. Required, unless
your cohort. Mask? Yes. You don't need the gown. You don't need the mask. You don't
need the mask. Gloves? Yes. Gown? Not necessarily. The gown is more for contact. It really, really
is. Hand washing? Yes. Eye face shields? No. No. Not really. You don't need the mask. Special
filter mask only for TB, only for tuberculosis. Patient wear mask when leaving room? Absolutely.
In fact, they really shouldn't be leaving the room in the first place. But if they do,
they have to wear the mask. Disposable supplies, dedicated equipment is probably a good thing,
but it's not as essential as in the other two. So you could let that one slide. You
could let that... Because it's what? Airborne, not droplet or contact. And negative airflow?
Yes. Now, the interesting thing about tuberculosis is how is tuberculosis spread by what method?
Droplet. But what precautions is it on? Airborne. See, so one of the two that don't make a lot
of sense, RSV and TB, they're both what? Droplet. One is however on contact, the other is on
airborne. But they're both transmitted via droplet. Question? Shingles would be herpes zoster,
so it is a contact. It's just, it's by the varicella, but it's not a respiratory varicella.
It's a contact varicella. Good question. The other thing that I want you to know, because
they're really, I mean, they're like, why don't rice on this one, is protect personal
protective equipment, PPE. And they want to know what order you put it on and what order
you take it off, because it's a drag and click or click and drag. Well, here's the deal.
You always take it off in alphabetical order. You take it off in the alphabetical order.
So, what would be the first thing you'd take off? Gown, mask, gloves or goggles? Gown,
gloves, mask or goggles? Make it alphabetical. What would come first? Gown, goggles, mask
or gloves? Gloves followed by goggles followed by gown followed by mask. So it comes off,
and it's hard for you right now to think alphabetical, right? But when you see it, you'll, and when
it's alphabetical, on or off? Off. Off is alphabetical. On is the reverse alphabetical
for the G's, but mask comes second. So what would you put it on? It's reverse alphabetical
for the G's, and mask comes second. So it's GMGG. Gown, mask, goggles, gloves. And then
it comes off, gloves, goggles, gown, mask. So off is easy, because it's alphabetical.
On, you got the G's are reverse alphabetical order, but the mask gets put in second. GMGGGGGM.
You see that? So that's the best way to go with that. Okay, turn the page to 50, and
it will be done. And then it will be about 10 after 9.
20 minutes early. Did I go too fast or? No. Feeling all right? Okay. Tomorrow morning's
going to come really soon, guys. Okay, by the time we end tomorrow, we will have barely
spent 24 hours together. By the time we end tomorrow, nice, that's quite intense. Okay,
I refuse to teach a math class, because everybody's math problem is a little different. Math is
best learned individually, not in a class. So what I want you to do is I want you to
try these math problems tonight or tomorrow night. Okay, the answers are at the bottom
of the page. Now, I was real sloppy with rounding, so as long as you're close to what I have,
you're probably right, I'm probably wrong. But as long as you're close to what I have,
you're probably okay. It's probably just a rounding error I made, and it's not your
problem. So what I want you to do is do these problems, see if you come up with the answers.
If you come up with the answers at the bottom of the page, guess what? We don't need to
talk. But if you can't get any of them, we better talk. Well, when should we talk? During
lunch, at the breaks, you know what I mean? Talk with me. So because we can help you with
this, the first two are what we call dosage calculation. It's when what the doctor orders
isn't what's on the bottom. There's no conversion involved. It's just a simple desired over
half times available, or if you're like me, just set up a ratio proportion. I was a math
major, a chemistry major first, and I had three quarters of calculus in differential equations.
So when we went to nursing, and they were teaching me this stupid little form of desired
over half, and I've had more math than all my faculty combined, it was like, what? But
if you know how to do it, do it. Okay, and the next one is the IV drip rates, and these
are mostly the RNs. You're going to have to know these LPNs. You may probably not have
to know these. But that's the volume times drop factor over time in minutes. Volume times
drop factor over time in minutes. That's your formula to memorize for that. Okay, and
remember, mini drip is 60 drops per mil. Mini, or micro, is 60. Macro is what? 10, or 20,
or 15, or 12. But boards will say it's 10, which is really stupid because all manufacturers
are different. Micro and mini are always 60. 60 drops per mil. That's your drop factor.
So when they say micro and mini, your drop factor is what? 60. So you're going to multiply
by 60 and then divide by 60, so what? Why bother? Right. I love mini drip calculations
for iDrip. Why do I like mini drip for IV drip rates? If you just divide the volume by the
hours, you got your answer. Because all you're going to do is multiply by 60, then divide
by 60. If you're going to do the same thing, why bother? Right. Okay. The next two are
pediatric dose questions where you're using the child's weight. And LPNs, they will give
you the easons. And it's 2.2 pounds per kilogram. They will always give you the kilogram weight,
always. They will never go the other way. They don't give you kilograms and ask for
pounds. They always give you pounds and ask for kilograms. So you're going to be what?
Dividing pounds by 2.2. You will always, listen to this, you will always be dividing by 2.2.
You will never be multiplying by it. So take the weight, divide by 2.2, then do your math.
Pay attention to whether they're asking the total amount per day or the amount to be given
at just one time. Does she have a second? Because if it says TID, then you're going to have
to divide by 2.2. And then divide by 2.2. And then divide by 2.2. And then divide by 2.2.
15 milligrams per kilogram per day TID. That means the whole daily dose is, and then you
have divided into what? Three to get what you're going to give at one time. But if they
say what's the daily dose, you give the whole, do you see where you have to pay attention
to what they're asking for? Are they asking for a dose at one time or the whole daily dose?
Because you can do the math right and still miss the question if you don't pay attention
to that. And the last two, last two are IV replacement questions. This is more for RNs.
And there's no formula for that one. It's just thinking with math. Now just a couple
of things about math real quick. Do you use leading zeros? Yes or no? Leading zeros? As
long as it maintains what? Place. So what about this? I'm sorry. 0 0 0. 0 0 3 0 0. How
many zeros are not needed and how many zeros are needed? Four are not needed. Two is three.
Three are. Three are. Okay. Needed or not needed? Not needed. Needed or not needed?
Needed. Needed. Needed. Needed. Needed. No. So note, you can use leading zeros as long
as they maintain place. You cannot, do not use trailing zeros. Ever. Also, fours will
tell you to what you are to round. Which I'm not. I think it's fantastic. They made
that change about four or five years ago to where they say round to nearest tenth. So
you don't have to sit there going, what should I round to? They told you nearest tenth. And
then you do not have to put units. If they say, how many milliliters will you give, just
write ten. Don't write ten m-m. Because that says, how many milliliters will you give? Ten
milliliters. You just have to say, you don't need these units. You just need the numbers.
Alright. And write the numbers. Don't write ten. Okay. Any questions? Alright. See you
tomorrow at what time? Nine. Nine. Right and early. I have an hour long to get home. Who
has longer? How long? Oh. Are you staying in or you're leaving? I'm leaving.
This isn't really a whole hour though. It's not really a whole hour.